hey everyone welcome back and today
let's not write some neat code because
today we are going to be quickly running
through the top five most common graph
algorithms for coding interviews so the
number one most common graph algorithm
you may have expected this is depth
first search dfs now the time complexity
of this algorithm in most cases is going
to be linear time in other words big o
of n where n is going to be the number
of nodes inside of our graph so if
you're familiar with graphs you know
that graphs are made up of nodes which
can contain values and also edges which
connect the nodes together if we have n
nodes then dfs runs in big o of n time
now what kind of data structures are
needed for dfs well if you are going to
do this recursively the only data
structure you will most likely need is
going to be a hash set the hash set is
specifically to basically detect a cycle
because depth for search is about
traversing a graph so for example if we
start at this position we want to
traverse the graph we go to the next
node we go to a another node over here
suppose these two nodes were connected
then we travel to this node and then
we'd get here and then we'd travel back
to this node which would get us stuck
into a cycle right now we don't want to
stay stuck in this cycle forever which
is why hash sets are required in many
cases for the dfs algorithm on a generic
graph if you are doing this recursively
you will not need a stack because the
recursion handles that for you but if
you do not do this recursively you can
optionally decide to use a stack for dfs
problems now let's suppose we were doing
a dfs on this graph let's say starting
from a now obviously this looks exactly
like a tree and yes it is a tree but we
know that trees are just special cases
of graphs so this is still a generic
graph now if we were starting here at
this a node and we were doing a dfs what
would be the output well the output we'd
first process the first node we'd get an
a then we'd go to the next node right
now dfs works basically going depth
first so so it's depth first so we we do
b now next we go to c you can see that
this is definitely depth first we're
going as deep as we can in one direction
so we get to c now now we can't go any
farther from c left or right so we go
back up and we go to the next node that
was available to us the farthest down
depth first right d
and now there's no more nodes anywhere
left over here so then we go to the next
node that was available which was e we
have done the entire graph and this is
the output abcde next let's go to our
second algorithm bfs or breadth first
search and as the name implies this is
also a searching algorithm which is
basically designed to traverse a graph
now this is going to be slightly
different than depth first search mainly
in the order that it traverses the
values which is what we're going to see
when i show you the output how d bfs
would traverse this graph but the time
complexity actually of this graph is
going to be the same as dfs because
we're going to visit each node at most
once so the time complexity is going to
be big o of n where n is the number of
nodes in the graph the data structures
typically needed for this algorithm and
it's usually not implemented recursively
so it usually requires a q data
structure a double-ended queue usually
again in in our graph we could have a
cycle similar to the dfs case so we
don't want to get stuck in a loop where
we go to one node go to the next node
and then just stay stuck in there
forever because we don't want to visit
the same node twice how can we avoid
that same case same way that we did in
dfs which is using a hash set to detect
duplicate nodes and bfs is kind of the
opposite of dfs so let's say we start at
the same first node right we start at a
so let's add a to the output now instead
of going the farthest we can in one
direction like we did before like going
to b and then going to c let's do
breadth first search right breath
meaning everything that's close to us
basically we're gonna do this layer
first right we're gonna we're gonna
traverse this entire layer and then
we're gonna traverse the next layer and
then keep doing that until we run out of
layers to traverse so let's go let's
first go to b so b is gonna be processed
adding it to the output then let's go to
e adding this to the output and you can
see that this is a different output than
we had when we ran dfs so this is a
different ordering that we're going to
traverse these nodes in so we've done
the second layer over here let's do the
next layer over here so we'll do c and
then d so let's add c and d to the
output and then you can see everything
has been processed in the entire graph
we had a slightly different output than
we did with the dfs case so the third
graph algorithm is definitely a little
bit different this is union find which
is used to kind of union together
disjoint sets and kind of combine them
together efficiently so the overall time
complexity of this algorithm is usually
bounded by n
log n
and in terms of data structures what
i'll say is just that it it requires
basically a forest of trees which is
really how i was taught how this is
implemented but basically you usually
have to implement union find yourself
the good thing is it's not super hard to
implement it because for example one
thing we could do with union find is
basically what if we wanted to know the
number of connected components of a
graph and we were given five different
nodes now of course in this case we have
five connected components each of these
is a component now but what if we start
arbitrarily adding edges if i say okay
i'm going to add an edge here i'm adding
one edge well that decreased the number
of components from five down to four now
now we only have four what if i take
another edge and increase it or add the
edge over here now we have three
different connected components what if i
take another edge and add it over here
well that didn't change anything we
still have one two three connected
components union find is basically an
algorithm that can do stuff like this
efficiently for us so suppose we added
these three edges now we want to know
how many connected components we have we
have three connected components exactly
three so three would be in the output
now this is a very high level overview
if you would like a more detailed
explanation of the union find algorithm
i would recommend watching this video
which is actually number of connected
components in an undirected graph which
we solved using union find
so the next algorithm on our list is
definitely one of the more difficult
ones and definitely more obscure you
don't see this algorithm used a lot but
it is topological sort and this
algorithm is actually built on top of
one of the previous algorithms dfs you
can see why dfs is so important because
it's actually used in a lot of other
algorithms including topological sort so
topological sort basically at a high
level is we are given a directed
acyclical graph basically a graph with
directed edges and the graph will not
have any cycles basically the
topological sort of a graph like this
one would be reading the values of every
single node in the graph but only and
basically printing those values out in
such an order that for example d when we
print d we have to make sure that every
node that came before it has already
been printed or processed or traversed
or whatever you want to call it so one
valid topological sort would be a b
c d and e a topological sort doesn't
have to be unique there's actually two
different topological sorts in this
graph we could do a and then we could do
b and then c or we could do c
and then do b that's two different
choices we have but once we do those
then the choices are limited then we
have two nodes left we have to do d
before we do e so one topological sort
could be a b c d e this is where we are
doing this with depth first search so
the overall time complexity is going to
be big o of n we are going to be using a
hash set since we are doing dfs but if
we do it recursively that should be the
only data structure that we actually
need this was a very quick explanation
of topological sort but if you would
like a more detailed solution and
explanation i would recommend watching
this video alien dictionary we
comprehensively explain topological sort
and then solve a problem using
topological sort and the last algorithm
i wanted to quickly go over is jixtra's
shortest path algorithm this is
definitely
a popular famous algorithm and it does
show up in leak code though it's not
super common in leak code and encoding
interviews but it's definitely a good to
know you'll definitely learn this in
school just like the name says it's
about finding the shortest path from one
node so let's say we had a starting node
a we want to find the shortest path from
a to every single node in the graph a b
c d e right we want to find the length
of the shortest path now the graphs
we've been looking at so far have been
pretty simple graphs right each edge
actually doesn't have any weight
associated with it each edge basically
has a weight of one right a simple
weight because they're all equal but we
could actually have edges of different
values suppose we had something like
this so this makes finding the shortest
path a little bit more difficult because
we actually have to look at the values
of every single edge in the graph now
and the overall time complexity of
jigsaw's algorithm is actually more
complex than a regular dfs it's
typically e log v where v is the number
of nodes or vertices in the graph e is
the number of edges in the graph it's a
little bit more complex
it's a little bit of a worse time
complexity because we have to deal with
these edges now how are we going to deal
with these edges what data structure are
we going to use a heap or a priority
queue however you want to call it is
usually the main data structure used to
find the shortest path because we're
going to have to be looking at the
minimum edge and we're going to have to
be looking at the minimum of many
different values so the heap is going to
be very helpful for doing that and you
still don't want to you know get stuck
in a cycle so hash sets are also helpful
for this algorithm and just to give you
a quick rundown of how this algorithm
would work on this example we'd start at
a we'd look at the shortest edge it's
one so then we'd get to b we'd say you
know the length to get to b is just
going to be one then we'd look at the
next two edges that are available to us
we'd choose the smaller one this one
which would get us to c so we'd say to
get to c it just takes a length of two a
weight of two and then we'd look at our
next uh frontier we could we could
choose the five or the two of course
we're going to choose the two so then
we'd say at this point d uh the cost to
get to d is actually four we don't just
include this single two but we also
include the previous two that it took
and then the last edge is e or the last
node is e how long does it take to get
to e basically
as far as it takes to get to d which is
four plus this one so e is five so this
is kind of the uh you know the shortest
paths to every single node in the out in
the graph and for a more in-depth look
at jigstra's algorithm i recommend
taking a look at this problem network
delay time i have a solution for this
problem on my channel and i think i go
over the entire concept of jigsaw's
algorithm in detail and then we write
out the code for that but that has been
the entire video that's the top five
most common algorithms in coding
interviews there are a couple more
algorithms that i do want to mention
though there's a couple more algorithms
that do sometimes come up in interviews
but they're pretty rare so the two are
i would recommend learning prims or
kruskal's algorithm for minimum spanning
trees both of the algorithms are pretty
comparable so i would say you only
really have to learn at least one of
them but if you want to learn both of
them they're pretty similar so you can
and this is for minimum spanning trees
and there's another algorithm which is
pretty similar to jixtra's algorithm
that can sometimes be useful in some
difficult problems and that is this
floyd were charles algorithm but this
one is definitely pretty rare i've
actually never seen this come up in any
coding interview of mine and i've never
heard of anybody getting this but some
sometimes it does happen so if you
really wanna but yeah that has been the
most common graph algorithms for coding
interviews i hope that this video was
helpful if it was please like and
subscribe and consider checking out my
patreon where you can further support
the channel i really appreciate all my
patreon supporters and hopefully i'll
see you pretty soon thanks for watching